דף *Daf* is ט"ו *Tes Vav*, we pick up on the bottom
of י"ח עמוד ט' *Yud Ches Amud Tes*, י"ד עמוד ב' *Yud
Daled Amud Beis* excuse me, ואינו עושה תמורה tmurah *ve'eino ose tmura*,
two lines before the lines get wide. And we're talking about a
קרבן korban *korban* that had a מום mum *mum* before it was
sanctified. So therefore the sanctity was never heading to the altar, קדושת
מזבח kedushas mizbeach, *kedushas mizbe'ach*. It was always to be redeemed. Redeemed
and then the money would be used for the altar, but never
to this animal itself to go to the altar. And then we're
talking about some of the consequences of this non-altar sanctity of קדושת
דמים kedushas damim. *kedushas damim*. So we say the following: ואינו עושה
תמורה tmurah *ve'eino ose tmura*, you cannot make an exchange. Meaning, not
make an exchange, but if you try to exchange another animal with
it, the other animal does not become קדוש Kadosh *kadosh*. The laws
of תמורה tmurah *tmura* do not apply. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama? *Mai
ta'ama*, what's the reason? דאמר קרא *D'amar kra*, the verse says לא
יחליפנו ולא ימיר אתו טוב ברע או רע בטוב *lo yachalifenu velo
yamir oso tov b'ra o ra b'tov*. So good for bad, bad
for good. And you have to understand that חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* bad
stands as the standard in the context of קרבנות korbanos. *korbanos* means
with a מום mum *mum*. So they say השתא רע בטוב אמרת
לא *hashata ra b'tov amart lo*, since the end of the verse
says רע בטוב *ra b'tov*, you can't exchange, like the verse says
טוב ברע או רע בטוב *tov b'ra o ra b'tov*. You can't
even try to exchange a bad animal for a good one, which
is an animal with a blemish for one without, this is again
how they're understanding it. So if at the end of the verse
it said it won't even let you exchange a bad for a
good, טוב ברע מבעיא *tov b'ra mibaya*, of course you can't exchange
a good for a bad. So why did the verse say don't
exchange a good for a bad? אלא *Ella*, what it's telling you
is טוב מעיקרא *tov me'ikara*, the reason it mentions good for bad
is it's obviously that that's prohibited, but it's to tell you that
that's the condition in which for which something can become a תמורה
tmurah, *tmura*. Only טוב מעיקרא עושה תמורה tmurah, *tov me'ikara ose tmura*,
only something that originally was good. Now it might have a blemish,
but it started off unblemished. That and the sanctity it had was
sanctity of the altar, קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach *kedushas mizbe'ach*, that can
do a תמורה tmurah *tmura*. רע מעיקרא *ra me'ikara*, something started bad,
meaning our משנה Mishnah *mishna*, started with a blemish, so the sanctity
it had was never sanctity of the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*, קדושת מזבח
kedushas mizbeach *kedushas mizbe'ach*. So in that case אינו עושה תמורה eino
oseh tmurah, *eino ose tmura*, it cannot do a תמורה tmurah *tmura*.
That's what we mean in
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* where it says לא יחליפנו טוב ברע *lo
yachalifenu tov b'ra*, don't switch something that started off good with something
bad. Okay, or רע בטוב *ra b'tov*, but the רע *ra* now
is qualified by the first phrase of טוב *tov*. Which means that
even when we're saying bad for good and that bad makes a
תמורה tmurah *tmura*, an animal with a מום mum *mum* can make
a תמורה *tmura*, that's only if it started off as a טוב
*tov*. Only if it started off unblemished and then got a מום
mum *mum*. But if it started off with a מום mum *mum*
and it never had a קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach *kedushas mizbe'ach*, then
it is not in the category of תמורה *tmura*.
So mean, okay, so if it started off good but now it's
bad and now you still can't switch it, that's
what the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* says.
Yeah, and then we're talking about something that started out bad.
Correct. That is not in the category of תמורה *tmura*. Now אם
im, מתו יפדו *im mesu yipadu*, these things which again started out
with a מום mum *mum* died, they can be redeemed because they
are only קדושת דמים kedushas damim. *kedushas damim* and they're only standing
to be redeemed. And we will see, thank you, we will see
why other things cannot be redeemed in a minute. Normal קדשי מזבח
Kodshei Mizbeach *kodshei mizbe'ach*, there are two reasons why things that have
קדושה kedusha *kedusha* for the altar cannot be redeemed if they die.
Let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav*, זו דברי רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *zu divrei Rabbi Shimon*,
this is the position of רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* דאמר
קדשי מזבח kodshei mizbe'ach היו בכלל העמדה והערכה ha'amadah v'ha'arachah. *d'amar kodshei
mizbe'ach hayu bichlal ha'amada veha'aracha*. Things relating to the altar, קדושה kedusha
*kedusha* for the altar, was in the paragraph where it says in
the תורה Torah *Torah* והעמידו הכהן והעריך אתו לפני ה' *vehe'emido hakohen
veha'arich oso lifnei Hashem*. The כהן kohen. *Kohen* will stand it up
and estimate its value, which means to say that it has to
be alive and you have to stand it up. And that idea
that an animal that you're redeeming has to be alive is only
קדשי מזבח kodshei mizbe'ach *kodshei mizbe'ach*. Only things for the altar. But
things that are קדשי דמים kodshei damim. *kodshei damim*, like something that
started with a blemish and its קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* was only for
value and not for the altar, that thing does not have to
be alive, that thing even if it's dead you can redeem. קדשי
בדק הבית Kodshei Bedek HaBayis לא היו בכלל העמדה והערכה ha'amadah v'ha'arachah
*kodshei bedek habayis lo hayu bichlal ha'amada veha'aracha*. Things that were for
the treasury were never in that category and therefore our משנה Mishnah
*mishna* is effectively something in that treasury, like something that was treasury,
not exactly, but it's value for the altar but nevertheless it's basically
for value and therefore it doesn't have to be alive. דתנן *Detnan*,
we taught in the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon אומר
*Rabbi Shimon omer*, קדשי בדק הבית Kodshei Bedek HaBayis אם im מתו
יפדו *kodshei bedek habayis im mesu yipadu*. This is a משנה Mishnah
*mishna* in תמורה *Temura*. קדשי בדק הבית kodshei bedek habayit אם מתו
יפדו *kodshei bedek habayis im mesu yipadu*, things that are for the
treasury if they die you can redeem, even animals. Even animals and
that's essentially our משנה Mishnah? *mishna*, which is the case where it
started with a מום mum *mum*. ומודי רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon בבעל
מום mum מעיקרא שנפדה
*umodei Rabbi Shimon b'ba'al mum me'ikara shenifda*. However, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon,
*Rabbi Shimon* does agree that if something started with giving, not a,
תוספות *Tosafot* says who's he agreeing to, but okay, the basis what
it is, although he says things for the altar cannot be redeemed
if they're dead, he admits that if it started with a blemish
and was then sanctified for the altar, which is our משנה Mishnah
*mishna*, right, and because it started with a blemish it never really
was fit for the altar, so that type of a thing he
admits that בשנפדה *b'shenifda* it can be redeemed, it's like something sanctified
for the Temple treasury. So basically we have an explicit משנה Mishnah
*mishna* in תמורה *Temura* which spells out the underlying logic of our
משנה Mishnah *mishna*. That things that were initially sanctified for the altar
and then got a blemish, once they're in the category of קדושת
מזבח kedushas mizbeach *kedushas mizbe'ach*, need to be alive to be redeemed.
Things that were never sanctified for the altar, which were like you
know, or they were sanctified but they started with a blemish, so
their sanctity was never fit for the altar, those things can be
redeemed even if they're dead. Now the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says מאי
טעמא *mai ta'ama*, what's the reason? דאמר קרא *d'amar kra*, אותה *osah*.
אותה *osah* למיעוטי בעל מום mum מעיקרא *l'mutei ba'al mum mei-ikara*. It
says והעמידה הכהן דערכה לפני השם *v'he'emida hacohen d'ercha lifnei Hashem*, or
what's the אותה *osah* פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? והעמיד אותה *v'he'emid osah*
might be, I might be misquoting the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* a little
bit. Okay, anyway, so it says you stand it, so would somebody
have the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* there? Whatever. Anyway, somebody will find the
פסוק *pasuk*. You stand it before God. So it, meaning only something
that is a full קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach *kedushas mizbe'ach* and not
something that you tried to make a קרבן korban *korban* but had
a blemish to begin with that is not fully in the category
of קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach *kedushas mizbe'ach*. Okay, so that's his reason.
Now, אבל aval, חכמים Chakhamim אומרים *aval chachamim omrim*, but the sages
say אם מתו יקברו *im mesu yikaveru*, if it dies you should
bury it, even this thing which started with a blemish. Okay, now
they don't, even an animal that started with a blemish, it needs
to be alive to be redeemed. Now we're going to see there
are two possible reasons why something would need to be alive. We've
already mentioned the idea of the verse in the Torah that you
should stand it before God, and what is the scope of that
verse? So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *gemara* and
the other possible reason. מאן חכמים Chakhamim *man chachamim*, who is the
חכמים Chakhamim *chachamim*? תנא דבי לוי tana devei Levi הוא hu. *tana
d'bei Levi hu*. It's the author from the house of Levi. דתנא
דבי לוי *d'tana d'bei Levi*, who taught from the house of Levi,
הכל היו בכלל העמדה והערכה ha'amadah v'ha'arachah *hakol hayu bichlal ha'amada v'ha'aracha*.
Everything is in the category of needing to be alive to be
valued and redeemed, even things that are not headed for the altar,
even animals that are just for the temple treasury. ואפילו בעל מום
mum מעיקרא *v'afillu ba'al mum mei-ikara*, even something that started with a
blemish. וכן תנא tanna דבי לוי במתניתא *v'chen tana d'bei Levi b'masnisa*,
and that's what Rabbi Levi taught in a ברייתא braita. *braisa*, אפילו
חיה chaya אפילו עוף *afillu chaya afillu of*, even if you sanctify
something that was never headed for the altar, a חיה chaya *chaya*,
עוף *of*, maybe it could be certain birds, but anyway, even a
חיה chaya *chaya*, even a deer, any animal, even something that was
never even possible to ever bring as a קרבן korban *korban*, any
animal that's sanctified even for the temple treasury needs to be alive
to be redeemed. That's what he understands the scope of the verse.
Okay, so that's one way you could say. So our משנה Mishnah
*mishna* that distinguishes between the type of קדושה kedusha *kedusha* understands that
the verse that says alive is only by altar sanctity, מזבח *mizbe'ach*,
not for קדושת בדק הבית *kedushas bedek habayis*, even this one that
was attempted to be מזבח *mizbe'ach* but got a blemish, whereas a
way, one way to disagree with this משנה Mishnah. *mishna* is to
say all animals have to be alive to be redeemed, I don't
care what purpose they're being sanctified for. Okay, והכתיב אותה *v'haksiv osah*,
doesn't it say you should stand it, which means it doesn't apply
to all animals? אותה לתנא דבי לוי קשיא *osah l'tana d'bei Levi
kashya*. Alright, we don't know what he'll do with that word. Moving
on. אבל רבנן rabbanan דפליגי עליה דרבי שמעון מאי *aval rabanan d'pligi
alei d'Rabbi Shimon mai*. Now, that's one way of arguing with Rabbi
Shimon, to say everything requires העמדה והערכה ha'amada ve'ha'aracha *ha'amada v'ha'aracha*. However,
there is a רבנן rabbanan, *rabanan* in תמורה *Temurah*, in that משנה
Mishnah *mishna* in תמורה *Temurah* of Rabbi Shimon's position that argue in
the opposite direction. They basically say that
you can redeem things with a blemish. So what's their logic? So
מאי *mai*, what would you say about the רבנן rabbanan *rabanan* that
argue on Rabbi Shimon? What is their, we haven't even quoted them,
that's true. Okay, but understanding that in that משנה Mishnah *mishna* there's
a חכמים Chakhamim *chachamim* that argue. Okay, that משנה Mishnah *mishna* in
תמורה *Temurah*. So now we're trying to figure out what is the
argument about, what would they say? So מאי *mai*, הכא נמי דמתו
יפדו *hacha nami d'mesu yifdu*? Would they say that even animals that
are sanctified for the altar can be redeemed if they're dead? Or
maybe if it has at least a blemish, no, that's our case,
excuse me. Would they say that even that can be redeemed if
they're dead? אי הכי i hachi, *ei hachi*, if that's true, then
זו דברי רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon. ומחלוקתו מיבעיא ליה *zu divrei Rabbi
Shimon u-machlokto mibaya lei*. When we said that our משנה Mishnah. *mishna*
that says when they're dead they can be redeemed, why did you
just say it's Rabbi Shimon? If even the sages that argue on
him, meaning you could argue on Rabbi Shimon by being more strict
or more lenient, right? You could say like תנא דבי לוי *tana
d'bei Levi*, which is every animal has to be alive, that's more
strict. You could argue like the חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* that say any
animal can be redeemed, even if it's dead. So if that's what
the חכמים *chachamim* say who argue on Rabbi Shimon, then our משנה
Mishnah. *mishna* that says it can be redeemed even goes according to
the חכמים *chachamim*. So let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara.
*gemara* says. Where are we holding? One minute. Okay, excuse me. Now
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says we're not going so far to suggest they
would say that even something ממש mamash *mamash* for the altar can
be redeemed if it's dead, then you don't have anything to talk,
that the פסוק *pasuk* has no scope. The פסוק *pasuk* says it
has to be alive. So it means that maybe they would admit
that the case of when it had a blemish to begin with.
But then it's exactly what Rabbi Shimon himself says, then there's no
debate. And then why don't we say that our משנה Mishnah. *mishna*
is the rabbis as well? So let's
take a look. So אמרי Amri, *amri*, so אמרי רב לרבי שמעון
בן לקיש *amri Rav l'Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish*. Ah, one minute, מיבעיא
ליה *mibaya lei*. So אמרי *amri*, you could say רב לרבי שמעון
בן לקיש *Rav l'Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish*, דאמר לרבנן קדשי בדק הבית
היו בכלל העמדה והערכה ha'amada ve'ha'aracha. קדשי מזבח kodshei mizbeach. לא היו
בכלל העמדה והערכה ha'amada v'ha'aracha. *d'amar l'rabanan kodshei bedek habayis hayu bichlal
ha'amada v'ha'aracha, kodshei mizbe'ach lo hayu bichlal ha'amada v'ha'aracha*. So רב *Rav*
that says it's only Rabbi Shimon, not the חכמים *chachamim*, so you
know why the חכמים *chachamim* argue? They argue not because they're more
lenient or more strict, they're actually the exact reverse of Rabbi Shimon.
They
say
that a קרבן korban, *korban* that dies you can redeem. If something
is for temple treasury, that's the case that the verse is talking
about. So meaning we know over there in the משנה Mishnah *mishna*,
it's a little confusing because we don't even have the משנה Mishnah
*mishna* in front of us, but we know over there in the
משנה Mishnah. *mishna* that there's a חכמים *chachamim* that argue. Now and
the חכמים say, so what exactly is this opposing חכמים and why
can't they be our משנה's Mishnah what we're saying? So one way
of explaining it is that they're the exact flip. They say that
קדשי בדק הבית need to be alive, קדשי מזבח do not need
to be alive, which is obviously not our משנה Mishnah because our
משנה Mishnah says when it had a מום mum you can redeem
it dead, when it didn't start with a מום mum you have
to it has to be alive. So that clearly is רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon. not the חכמים that would say the exact opposite.
ולא מצית מוקמת מתניתין כרבנן V'lo matzit mokmat matnisin k'rabbanan and therefore
it can't be the Rabbis. Why? Because they say, first of all,
they say קדשי בדק הבית requires to be alive and in the
beginning of the משנה Mishna. it can be dead. But even if
you were to fudge that point that well it started with קדושת
מזבח, kedushas mizbeach but how about the end of the משנה? Mishna,
דקתני סיפא D'kasani seifa ואם מתו יקברו v'im meisu yikaveiru that if
an animal started with קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach and it then it
had a blemish and then died, you have to bury it. ממאי
Mimay why? דהמתים יקברו משום דבעי העמדה והערכה D'hameisim yikaveiru mishum d'ba'ei
ha'amadah v'ha'arachah הוא. hu. I'm sorry. So therefore you see that our
משנה Mishna is not the רבנן rabbanan is not the Rabbis that
argue on רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon, because our משנה mishna, at the
end says that if it started with קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach you
have to bury it and the Rabbis say that if something started
with קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach the חכמים who argue on רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon, you can redeem it even if it's dead. Now the
גמרא Gemara says one minute there could be another reason you can't
redeem an something that is sanctified once it's dead, not just what
in the scope of this verse of העמדה והערכה. ha'amada v'ha'aracha. There's
another issue. ממאי דהמתים יקברו משום דבעי העמדה והערכה? Mimay d'hameisim yikaveiru
mishum d'ba'ei ha'amadah v'ha'arachah? Who says it's because of this issue that
it needs to be alive and about whether it's in the פרשה?
parsha? There's another reason you could require an animal to be alive.
Why? דילמא משום דאין פודין את הקדשים להאכילן לכלבים Dilma mishum d'ein
podin es hakodoshim l'ha'achilan l'klavim הוא. So no, there's another reason. The
other reason is you can't redeem sacrifices if they're going to be
dog food. Okay, and therefore it has nothing to do with what
the verse allows or not. It's more of a rabbinic concern and
where is it headed and that it's not appropriate to redeem sacrifices
if they're going to wind up as dog food. Now what is
the difference between that reason and the other reason of whether they're
in the פסוקים? psukim? Either way you can't do it. Maybe you
could say maybe one is biblical, one is rabbinic, maybe בדיעבד b'di'eved
if you did it does it work? Those are all possible differences.
There's also a difference of scope. If you can't redeem it if
it's going to be dog food, let's say it's alive and it's
a טרפה. treifah. So that's something that is in the category of
העמדה והערכה ha'amada v'ha'aracha which just requires that it be alive but
it's but you're not going to ever be able to eat it
because if it's a טרפה treifah you're gonna have to turn it
into dog food. So that would not be allowed. So there are
two very different reasons why one is גזירת הכתוב gzeiras hakasuv is
it in the category or not which might even mean that בדיעבד
b'di'eved it doesn't work, and the other is is it appropriate to
do because it's heading off to be dog food and that is
a different scope that would apply even to something like a טרפה.
treifah. So now where are we? Our משנה Mishnah, says that when
it starts with a blemish then you can redeem it even if
it died. That is רבי Rebbe that and if it started without
a blemish you can't. The simplest way to explain that is רבי
שמעון Rebbe Shimon who says exactly that point. That it's קדושת מזבח
kedushas mizbeach it needs to be alive, not קדושת דמים. kedushas damim
If it starts with a blemish it's קדושת דמים. kedushas damim. Very
simple. The גמרא's Gemara trying to say well maybe even the sages
would agree. Why? Maybe the first state maybe the sages would say
that you can't redeem קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach but you can redeem
קדושת דמים kedushas damim and they would still say that the reason
you can redeem it in the רישא reisha is קדושת דמים. kedushas
damim Why can't you redeem it in the סיפא? seifa? Excuse me.
The reason you could redeem it in the רישא reisha is קדושת
מזבח kedushas mizbeach because it at least tried to be קדושת מזבח
kedushas mizbeach although it failed, and the reason you can't redeem it
in the סיפא seifa is because of even though it's in the
category of העמדה והערכה but אין פודין את הקדשים להאכילן לכלבים. ein
podin es hakodoshim l'ha'achilan l'klavim. Okay, that's a very hard argument because
then why don't you have that concern in the רישא reisha as
well? So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara אמרי, so first so it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara
that's sort of the most obvious question, but anyway the גמרא Gemara
asks another question. אם כן נתני נעשו טרפה יקברו. Im kein nisni
na'asu treifah yikaveiru. Why do you only say that if they die
they have to be buried? Why not say even a lesser case
like I said even if it's a טרפה treifah you can't? So
so therefore ואי בעית אימא, v'ee ba'is eima, so anyway the point
is is that it was a very funny אוקימתא ukimta because if
they really are saying that the only the concern is that you
can't redeem it להאכילן לכלבים, l'ha'achilan l'klavim, that should have been a
concern in the רישא reisha of the משנה as well. So that's
one aspect. One aspect is that it's not the רבנן, the רבנן
say the reverse of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon clearly that's not our
משנה. Our משנה is that it's קדושת דמים kedushas damim can be
redeemed, קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach. cannot. The רבנן say the reverse and
that's why we said our משנה is רבי שמעון. ואי בעית אימא
V'ee ba'is eima if you want לעולם רב כרבי יוחנן סבירא ליה.
l'olam Rav k'Rebbe Yochanan sevira lei. It's true. You know what? We
could say that the Rabbis are just as maybe basically say the
exact same position of רבי שמעון. They basically say קדושת דמים kedushas
damim if it starts with a מום mum it can be redeemed
you know and if it's קדושת דמים kedushas damim. it can excuse
me if it starts with a
מום mum it can
be redeemed קדושת דמים kedushas damim it can be redeemed קדושת מזבח
kedushas mizbeach cannot be redeemed and since זהו דברי רבי שמעון ומחלוקתו,
zeihu divrei Rebbe Shimon u'machlokso, when we say our משנה's רבי שמעון,
we don't only mean רבי שמעון, we mean רבי שמעון and the
חכמים over there in the משנה. Now it was a very complicated
גמרא Gemara I admit because we hadn't seen the משנה. So we
didn't even know what the context of the discussion was. But the
upshot is the following.
What is an animal, does an animal need to be alive or
dead in order to redeem it if it's sanctified? So one concern
we have פודים את הקדשים להאכילם לכלבים. podim es hakodashim le'achilam laklavim.
Now that is a concern that by the way answered the question
that Michael asked, could be that it's limited specifically to קרבנות. korbanot,
Maybe it's not to קדשי דמים. Again the same point, something that
was heading for the מזבח you don't want to turn into dog
food. Something that was basically getting the value out of it maybe
you could turn it into dog food. So that's one concern and
that could be focused on the קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf something that
was a קרבן korban but that has a different scope. A, that's
maybe לכתחילה lechatchila not a בדיעבד. bedieved. Number two is that it
would apply even to a טרפה treifa and so on. That's one
reason. Okay, the other issue is what is in the Torah's category
when it says והעמיד והעריך. ve'he'emid ve'he'erich. Now within what's in the
Torah's category you have a range of options. You could say only
קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbeiach. is in, not קדושת דמים. kedushas damim That's
the simplest way of explaining our משנה. When it starts with a
מום mum, קדושת דמים kedushas damim, it's not in the category. When
it doesn't start with a מום mum קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbeiach, is
and therefore it has to be alive. There's another possibility which basically
says the exact flip. Okay, if it's the exact flip that does
not seem to work at all with our משנה although the גמרא
Gemara tries to say maybe our משנה is not talking at all
about concerns about העמדה והערכה just פודים את הקדשים להאכילם לכלבים. podim
es hakodashim le'achilam laklavim. But that was a challenge. I don't know,
who knows, the פסוקים pesukim aren't clear what they're talking about and
it says וזאת. ve'zos. Anyway the final thing that the
גמרא gemara says is it applies to everything which is what the
גמרא gemara said thank you which is תנא דבי לוי and therefore
for another reason it can't be our משנה. So again in our
משנה that it's not a problem to redeem it with a when
it started with a מום mum it is when it didn't could
be for the reason it is a problem when it started without
a מום mum when it started קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbe'ach, there are
two particular problems. Number one it might be דוקא davka that case
that's in the Torah's category for העמדה והערכה. And number two it
might be דוקא davka that case that has the special problem of
פודים את הקדשים להאכילם לכלבים. podim es hakodashim le'achilam laklavim. When it
starts as קדושת דמים kedushas damim. you have at least according to
רבי שמעון neither of those concerns. Okay let's move on. That was
complicated enough especially without looking at the משנה and knowing what the
חכמים were talking about. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this אבל קדם הקדשן. aval kodem hekdeshan. Now we move on to
the second case which is it started with a קדושה kedusha and
then it got a blemish. So this is classic קדושת הגוף. kedushas
haguf. It's קדושת מזבח kedushas mizbeach, it started with קדושת מזבח kedushas
mizbeach, except now it got the מום mum, so now the question
is what do you do with it you have to redeem it
etc. but there it really has residual קדושה kedusha because it started
with קדושת מזבח. So
מנא הני מילי mena hanei milei where's this from? דתנו רבנן detanu
rabanan צבי. tzvi. Now the question we're asking is how do you
know after you've redeemed it if it still has residual קדושה. kedusha
Now one way to evidence the residual קדושה Kedusha. is the fact
that the Torah says right תזבח ואכלת בשר tizbach ve'achalta basar you
shall slaughter and eat the meat and the חז"ל Chazal understand that
means you only what can you do with a קרבן korban, that
was redeemed you can only eat the meat. You can't milk it
you can't shear it you can't work it and so on. That
proves that if it started with a full קדושת מזבח it retains
residual קדושה Kedusha even after it's redeemed. How do we know that
that residual קדושה Kedusha, is significant enough to tell us that even
now it is exempt from בכור bechor and even now it is
exempt from מתנות? matanos? So that's what we're going to see. דתנו
רבנן detanu rabanan we taught צבי. tzvi. It says just like you
eat the צבי tzvi and the איל ayal which is I think
whatever a hart or some type of deer you shall eat this.
And they understand that that's talking about a קרבן korban? that was
had a blemish later and then was redeemed. So מה צבי ma
tzvi it's just like a deer the same way a deer פטור
מן הבכורה patur min habechora you don't give firstborn why because you
only give firstborn from sheep goats and cows not from deer. So
אף פסולי מוקדשין פטורים מן הבכורה af pesulei mukdashin peturim min habechora
even something that was had a full קדושה Kedusha and then got
a blemish and was redeemed פסולי מוקדשין pesulei mukdashin also is exempt
from בכור. bechor. אוציא אני את הבכורה ולא אוציא את המתנות otzi
ani es habechora velo otzi es hamatanos maybe I'll only exclude בכורה
bechora but I won't exclude the gifts to the כהן. We'll see
in a minute why I would have thought those were treated differently.
תלמוד לומר איל Talmud lomar ayal it also compares it to an
איל ayal which is another type of a חיה chayah, like a
deer. מה איל פטור מן הבכורה ma ayal patur min habechora that's
also ומן המתנות umin hamatanos the same way an איל ayal is
exempt not only from firstborn but also from the מתנות matanos again
because מתנות matanos are also from only sheep goats and cows. So
אף פסולי מוקדשין פטורים af pesulei mukdashin peturim it's true about צבי
tzvi as well but if you only had one word you would
have only applied it to the more obvious exclusion. Because you have
two words it's not that איל ayal has a is more exempt
than a צבי tzvi but regardless but if you only had one
word you would have only exempted it from one thing because you
had two words you exempt it from both categories. Okay but we'll
talk but not necessarily maybe you would have only done the most
obvious we'll see why בכור bechor is more obvious. אף פסולי מוקדשין
פטורים מן הבכורה ומן המתנות. af pesulei mukdashin peturim min habechora umin
hamatanos. Now אם הצבי ואיל חלבן מותר im hatzvi ve'ayal chelban mutar
maybe I should say oh it's just like a deer and a
whatever a hart that their fat is permissible there's no איסור חלב.
issur chelev. So אף פסולי מוקדשין חלבן מותר af pesulei mukdashin chelban
mutar so maybe this is really treated like a צבי tzvi and
an איל ayal and maybe therefore their fat is permissible right which
seems a little bit absurd to really treat them like a חיה
chayah but nevertheless. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar אך ach it says however
just like you eat the צבי tzvi and איל ayal you should
eat this which means don't go overboard not fully and it's not
treated like a חיה chayah? that their fat is permissible. So it's
actually quite fascinating how. how far חז"ל Chazal will go sometimes to
this comparison to the צבי והאייל. tzvi v'ha'ayal. There's one opinion that
actually if you mate פסולי מוקדשין psulei mukdashin with it with another
פסולי מוקדשין psulei mukdashin you're חייב chayav for כלאים kilayim because it's
like they are a hybrid צבי ואיל tzvi v'ayal and like you're
mixing two species. That's really an extreme application, but you see they
take the verse quite seriously so there could have been a הוה
אמינא havamina that even the fat is permissible and you need אך
ach to exclude it. So now we're going to look at this
ברייתא. braita אמר מר, Amar Mar, הוציא את הבכור ולא הוציא את
המתנות. hotzi et habachor v'lo hotzi et hamatanot. If I had only
one word I would have excluded this פסולי מוקדשין, psulei mukdashin, this
redeemed sacrifice, from firstborn but not from מתנות. matanot. מאי שנא הוציא
את הבכור? Mai shna hotzi et habachor? Why is it more, why
is it clearer that you should not apply the בכור? bachor?
שאין שוה בכל. She'ein shaveh bakol. So, I'm sorry, מאי שנא, mai
shna, why is it any given, why would I have thought that
בכור bachor was more obvious? הוציא את הבכור שאין שוה בכל Hotzi
et habachor she'ein shaveh bakol because בכור bachor does not apply to
all animals. בכור Bachor anyway has more limited scope, it only applies
to firstborn males. It doesn't apply to all animals, to all animals.
So since it has more limited scope, it's the first thing to
go. ולא הוציא את המתנות ששוה בכל V'lo hotzi et hamatanot sheshaveh
bakol and I might not have excluded מתנות matanot that has a
broader scope, it applies to all animals, male or female, firstborn or
non-firstborn. So it would not have been so clear to me to
exclude that thing which has a larger scope. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar
איל ayal and therefore because it says a second word, that a
second חיה, chayah so that tells me to exclude it fully the
same way a חיה chayah. is fully excluded. Okay. אמר ליה רב
פפא לאביי. Amar lei Rav Papa l'Abaye. So רב פפא Rav Papa
said to אביי, Abaye, one minute, I have the following question about
how if we're taking this comparison to צבי ואיל tzvi v'ayal seriously.
Why don't I say, אם כצבי וכאיל אין אותו ובנו נוהג בהן
אף פסולי מוקדשין אין אותו ובנו נוהג בהן. im k'tzvi v'ayal ein
oto v'beno noheig bahen, af psulei mukdashin ein oto v'beno noheig bahen.
You know what else doesn't apply to חיה? What else doesn't apply
to חיה is the prohibition of shechting an animal and its child
on the same day. That only applies to a בהמה behemah and
not to a חיה. So why don't I say it doesn't apply
to פסולי מוקדשין? psulei mukdashin? And presumably we're not prepared to say
אין הכי נמי. ein hachi nami. So if you know how do
I know not to say that?
So he
says back to him, למאי מדמית לה? L'mai midamset lah? No, no,
no, that's a crazy comparison because forget the צבי ואיל. tzvi v'ayal.
This animal is either like חולין chullin or like קדשים. kodshim. The
fact that it's somewhere between the two doesn't mean it's going to
be different from both of them. So either category you put it
in, whether you put it in the חולין chullin category or the
קדשים kodshim category, it's going to be have the prohibition of אותו
ובנו. oto v'beno. You might remember that משנה by אותו ובנו oto
v'beno that had all those fun permutations of how many עבירות aveiros
you can be over by shechting אותו ובנו oto v'beno that's קדשים
בחוץ. kodshim bachutz. So he says look, either way, אי חולין, i
chullin, if you want to say it should be like חולין chullin
like non-sanctified animals, אותו ובנו נוהג בו. oto v'beno noheig bo. So
we know that applies, the prohibition of a mother and the child.
ואי קדשים, V'i kodshim, if by קדשים, kodshim, אותו ובנו נוהג בו.
oto v'beno noheig bo. So it applies. So he says don't go
overboard with this comparison of צבי ואיל. tzvi v'ayal. At the end
of the day, this animal is somewhere midpoint between חולין chullin and
קדשים kodshim and it's not going to have a different הלכה halakhah
than both חולין chullin and קדשים. kodshim. So then רב פפא Rav
Papa comes back to אביי Abaye and says, ah you can't say
that, because if that were true everything else would have been obvious
as well, right? So he said back to him, אי הכי, i
hachi wait a minute, where am I? אמר ליה, Amar lei, אי
הכי גבי חלבו נמי, i hachi gabei chelbo nami, why did we
need a verse for the fat? Why do we say ah צבי
ואיל tzvi v'ayal like the fat, we need a verse. According to
you, that was a silly point because it's obviously the fat is
forbidden because the fat of קדשים kodshim and the fat of חולין
chullin is forbidden. So
אי הכי חלבו נמי נימא הכי, chelbo nami neima hachi, למאי מדמית
לה? l'mai midamset lah? What are you going to compare it to?
Doesn't matter. אי חולין, I chullin, חלבו אסור, chelbo assur, if it's
for non-sanctified animals, their fat is forbidden. אי קדשים, I kodshim, חלבו
אסור, chelbo assur, and if it's for קדשים, kodshim, their fat is
forbidden. So we didn't say that, we didn't say look, it's not
really a צבי ואיל, tzvi v'ayal, it's somewhere between חולין chullin and
קדשים. kodshim. We took the comparison in the פסוק seriously. אלא לאו
מי אמרת אך ולא חלבו. Ella lav mi amart ach v'lo chelbo.
So therefore, what's the real answer, says רב פפא Rav Papa to
אביי, Abaye, you can't say like you, oh don't take צבי ואיל
tzvi v'ayal seriously. Here's the answer. The same way we used אך
ach to say that the fat was not, don't take the comparison,
that's what limited us taking the comparison to the end. אך Ach
says don't compare to the end like a צבי. tzvi. אך Ach
limits it. And therefore the fat is forbidden. אך ולא חלבו. Ach
v'lo chelbo. So אימא נמי אך ולא אותו ובנו. eima nami ach
v'lo oto v'beno. So we should say the same type of דרשה.
drasha. אך Ach limits it to אותו ובנו. oto v'beno. Now maybe
it's informed by the logic that there's no logic to make it
different than חולין chullin and קדשים, kodshim, but you can't just say
that by the virtue of the logic itself. We take the verse
seriously that says צבי ואיל tzvi v'ayal and then we need the
אך ach to you know to limit that. Again, the logic of
limiting might be exactly the point that you're making about why should
it be more lenient than both חולין chullin and קדשים kodshim together.
Okay, but at least don't tell me just by the logic, the
verse compares it to צבי ואיל, tzvi v'ayal, you need אך ach
to draw the line. That's what רב פפא Rav Papa says. רבא
אמר, Rava amar, so you see
is it Rava has a question?
Well or he still says if there is an answer then the
answer has to be that אך ach limits both. Maybe he's still
bothered why the ברייתא braita, didn't mention that but that has to
be the answer.
Yeah, and again, and yeah, and again that could be informed by
the logic of not worse than קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, but it
still has to in the end be anchored in the אך. ach.
Okay. So now that's רב פפא. Rav Pappa. רבא אמר Rava amar
so Rava says, where's
Rava? רבא אמר אך לאותו ואת בנו הוא דאתא. Rava amar ach
le'oto ve'et beno hu de'ata. You know what Rava says? I like
your question so much I'm gonna say the following: that really, ignore
the ברייתא, braita we'll get back to the ברייתא braita. in a
minute. אך ach is exactly limits אותו ואת בנו. oto ve'et beno.
It can't limit both. Okay,
maybe actually it's not exactly clear how to read the last line
of רב פפא. Rav Pappa. Maybe רב פפא Rav Pappa said you
need an אך ach to limit אותו ואת בנו oto ve'et beno
and you don't have it. So it might have ended more as
a question than as a statement. Okay, what? Okay, so fine, it's
not exactly clear. So anyway, the point is why you need something
like an אך ach and you don't have it. So רבא Rava
will say: You know what? You're right. אך לאותו ואת בנו הוא
דאתא. Ach le'oto ve'et beno hu de'ata. You're right, אך ach actually
is excluding אותו ואת בנו. oto ve'et beno. וחלבן? vechelban? So how
do we know the fat is forbidden if we don't have an
אך ach for that? An אך ach can only be used for
one thing. מדמו נפקא. midamo nafka. It's actually learned out from the
fact that the Torah explicitly prohibits its blood. The blood of פסולי
המוקדשין. pesulei hamukdashin. דכתיב: dechtiv: רק את דמו לא תאכל. rak et
damo lo tochal. Don't eat the blood, spill it on the ground
like water.
מאי דמו? mai damo? What does the Torah mean when it says
blood? אילימא דמו ממש? ilima damo mamash? If it really means blood?
לא יהא אלא דמה דצבי ואיל. lo yehei ela dama detzvi ve'ayal.
Ah, now you've now there's no reason for the Torah to say
you can't eat the blood. Because once it's compared to a צבי
ואיל, tzvi ve'ayal, right, so as חולין, chullin, as קדשים, kodshim, its
blood is forbidden. Even if it's compared to a doe and a
hart, its blood is forbidden. So why did the Torah say don't
eat the blood? We know you can't eat blood of animals. אי
ל- צבי
ואיל, ei le- tzvi ve'ayal, לא יהא אלא דמה דצבי ואיל. lo
yehei ela dama detzvi ve'ayal. אטו דמה דצבי ואיל מי שרי? atu
dama detzvi ve'ayal mi shari? Since when is the blood of a
doe or a deer permitted? So why did the Torah have to
prohibit the blood once it compared it to these animals? אלא דמו
ela damo when the Torah says don't eat the blood, it doesn't
really mean blood. It means חלבן chelban don't eat the fat.
ולכתוב רחמנא חלבן? velichtov rachmana chelban? Well let's see the end of
this חלבן. chelban. If it wanted to say that, why did it
say don't eat the fat? נו. nu. אי כתב רחמנא חלבן? ei
katav rachmana chelban? If חלב chelev it had said that, הוה אמינא
hava amina I would have said אהני היקישא ואהני קרא ahani hekesha
ve'ahani kra that the prohibition of the fat of these animals is
somewhere between the classic prohibition and not being prohibited at all. On
the one hand it's linked to the deer, which means which fat
is not forbidden. On the other hand the verse saying don't eat
the fat. But that would have ended me up midpoint. What would
have been
midpoint? אהני היקישא ahani hekesha linked to the deer למיעוטיה מכרת, lemieutei
mikaret, to say there's no prohibition of
כרת. karet. ואהני קרא ve'ahani kra דכי כתיב כרת, dechtiv karet, אוכל
חלב בהמה הוא דכתיב. ochel chelev behema hu dechtiv. When you eat
the fat of a בהמה, behema, that's the only fat that's prohibited,
שנאמר: shenemar: כי כל אוכל חלב מן הבהמה. ki kol ochel chelev
min habehema. If you eat the חלב chelev from a בהמה, behema,
then you get כרת. karet. ואהני קרא ve'ahani kra the verse that
said it still is prohibited and don't compare it to a deer
altogether למיקם עליה בלאו בעלמא, lemekam aleih belav be'alma, to tell me
that there's a simple לאו. lav. So meaning, the Torah could not
have said what it needed to say. It couldn't have said the
fat is prohibited, because if it said the fat is prohibited you'd
say, oh yes, it's very nice you say the fat is prohibited,
but you're also telling me it's like the צבי והאיל. tzvi veha'ayal.
So what I'll interpret what it means the fat is prohibited is
it's a new prohibition of fat, not the classic one. The classic
one only applies to בהמה. behema. This is being compared to a
deer, so it's not the classic prohibition that there's כרת. karet. It's
a new prohibition of fat without כרת. karet. That's what I would
have said. So if it just prohibited fat I would have said,
a new prohibition without כרת. karet. So therefore להכי אפקיה רחמנא בלשון
דמו. lehachi afkeih rachmana bilshon damo. Therefore it says the blood, למימר
לך, leimar lach, מה דמו בכרת אף חלבן בכרת. ma damo bekaret
af chelban bekaret. That blood you don't need me to tell you,
you know that blood is forbidden. Why am I saying blood? To
tell you everything that's like blood. The same way the blood, the
other things that are prohibited classically remain prohibited here. It means blood
also means fat, and just like blood is כרת, karet, fat is
כרת. karet. אשכחן קמאי, ashkechan kamai, which means
yeah, well we learn a lot of things from אשכחן קמאי. ashkechan
kamai. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara like about different ways of קרבנות,
Korbanot whatever, anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says,
we're talking about blood.
All right, so you know, we're talking about both things at the
same time. But at some level we're talking about fat.
והתנא אך דלאו חלבן קאמר. vehatanna ach delav chelban ka'amar. How could
you say that? Our תנא says אך ach is to limit חלבן.
chelban. And you're saying אך ach is to limit אותו ואת בנו,
oto ve'et beno, and חלבן chelban we learn out from דמה? dama?
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is how you read the
ברייתא. Beraita אילו לא נאמר דמו, ilu lo ne'emar damo, היית אומר
אך ולא חלבן. hayit omar ach velo chelban. I would have used
it to exclude חלבן. chelban. עכשיו שנאמר דמו, achshav shene'emar damo, but
I really don't even need it for that because I know the
חלבן chelban is forbidden because it because it says the blood. So
אותו ואת בנו הוא דאתא. oto ve'et beno hu de'ata. The אך
ach is coming to exclude אותו ואת בנו. oto ve'et beno. So
this is all רב פפא's Rav Pappa's question, which is, you know,
if you take the comparison seriously, then you need to exclude more
than just fat, you need to exclude אותו ואת בנו. oto ve'et
beno. And therefore רבא Rava tries this creative answer, which is rereading
it and saying you're right, that is what אך ach is doing,
חלבן chelban is coming is actually learned from this idea of דמו.
damo. But again, what it does point to is, you know, where
אביי's Abaye's answer is really the answer we would have said, which
is: let's give me a break, let's not go overboard with this
comparison, okay, and let's talk, you know, this is not going to
be something that is worse than both קדשים kodshim and חולין. chullin.
Okay. But you know, but רב פפא Rav Pappa says that's not
the assumption. The ברייתא braisa takes it seriously and needs פסוקים, Pesukim,
and that leads us down the road that we have. But what
we do learn out from the comparison is that it is exempt
from בכור Bechor and מתנות. Matanot. And I should say by the
way at the end of the day using אביי's Abaye logic, how
do I think in my head why is it exempt from בכור
Bechor and מתנות? Matanot? So I think, well because the תורה Torah
compared it to a deer? No. Presumably the reason I say at
the end of the day it's exempt from בכור Bechor and מתנות
Matanot is because it has residual קדושה. Kedusha, And the same way
something that's really קדוש kadosh is exempt from בכור Bechor and מתנות,
Matanot, something like this that has residual קדושה Kedusha, remains exempt from
קרבנות Korbanot and from בכור Bechor and מתנות, Matanot, which is in
the end is אביי's Abaye point. That the reason is not the
פסוק comparing it to the deer, the reason is because it's not
yet fully in the category of חולין. Chulin. It's still to some
degree in the category of קדשים Kodshim and therefore it's exempt from
קרבנות and from בכור Bechor and מתנות, Matanot, which is the point
of our משנה. Okay, so that's point number one. After you've redeemed
it, when it started with full קדושה, Kedusha it has residual קדושה
Kedusha and it is exempt from בכור Bechor and מתנות. Matanot. And
now we actually go to the more obvious point of residual קדושה,
Kedusha which is that after you've redeemed it, when it started with
full and then got the blemish, you cannot work it, you cannot
shear it, you cannot milk it. You have the only thing you're
allowed to do is שחט shecht it and eat it. So ואינם
יוצאים לחולין להיגזז ולהיעבד. v'einam yotzim l'chulin l'higazez u'l'he'aved. Honey, really? Where
do I know you can't shear it and work it? דתנו רבנן
D'tanu rabanan we taught, תזבח, Tizbach, it says however you shall slaughter
and eat meat. Again, it's a verse that the context is not
clear and חז"ל tell us that this is talking about a verse
of פסולי המוקדשין. Psulei HaMukdashin. So תזבח Tizbach and we read it
the following way: slaughter it בלא גיזה, belo giza, don't shear. בשר,
Basar, you can eat the meat בלא חלב, belo chalav, you cannot
get the milk. Okay, this is the only thing you're allowed to
do with פסולי המוקדשין Psulei HaMukdashin is to have a permission to
eat it. ואכלת, V'achalta, you should eat it ולא לכלבך, v'lo l'kalbecha,
not for your dogs. Okay, which means tells us the point that
we told earlier, מכאן שאין פודים את הקדשים להאכילם לכלבים. mikan she'ein
podim et hakodshim l'ha'achilam l'klavim. And now we're saying as opposed to
what I was suggesting earlier, here we're actually learning it from the
verse and therefore it is דאורייתא, De'oraita, okay, and you are not
allowed to redeem it if it's
if it's טריפה treifa or if it's a מתה, meita, a נבילה,
neveila, then you cannot redeem it. You're only allowed to redeem it
for the sake that you should be able to eat from it.
And once you've redeemed it, you can't do anything else than eating
from it. And this is at least this way of reading the
verse is tells us this idea of אין פודים את הקדשים, ein
podim et hakodshim, at least קדשי מזבח you can't redeem. Again, קדשי
בדק הבית you can, that was the first half of our משנה,
but קדשי מזבח you cannot redeem because it had that full קדושה,
Kedusha, it was headed to the altar. It's headed to the altar,
can't wind up as dog food. You can redeem it if you're
going to eat it, you can't do anything else than eating it,
and you can't redeem it for dog food. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri,
others say one minute, תזבח ואכלת, Tizbach v'achalta, they make the דרשה
drasha slightly differently. You should slaughter and eat.
They don't learn it from each word, תזבח Tizbach and not that,
ואכלת v'achalta and not that, you know, ולא לכלבך. v'lo l'kalbecha. They
just learn it out from the more general sense of the verse.
The תורה Torah says slaughter and eat it. So what are you
allowed to do with קדשים? Kodshim? You're allowed all you can do
is eat it. You can't work it, you can't shear it, you
can't milk it, you can only eat it with קדשים Kodshim that
you've redeemed. אלא משעת זביחה ואילך, Ela mishat zvicha v'eilach, all you
can do get benefit is after it's been slaughtered. You can get
no benefit prior to being slaughtered, which is things like shearing it,
working it, and milking it. Now אבל, but since you can get
benefit after it's been slaughtered, פודים את הקדשים להאכילם לכלבים. podim et
hakodshim l'ha'achilam l'klavim. But however, you could redeem it to turn it
into dog food if it if it died on you. Well, that's
a question of העמדה והערכה. Let's take an easier case, if it's
a טריפה, treifa, there would be no problem because the תורה's Torah
not saying only you can eat it, it's saying you can only
get the benefit that you come after you slaughter. While it's alive,
it's the קדושה kedusha. has to be attended to. Once it's been
slaughtered, it's fine and therefore you can actually use it for dog
food. Can you redeem it once it's dead? That's the question of
העמדה והערכה. But here the question would be like here's an you
know, here the question would be let's say it's a טריפה, treifa,
it's not even a העמדה והערכה question and this is where we
see the biblical basis of this idea of פודים את הקדשים להאכילם
לכלבים. podim et hakodshim l'ha'achilam l'klavim. Okay, yes Michael.
Just a quick question, because let's say a sanctified animal, you're saying
that the animal, you can't let the kids suck from it, right?
What?
What if it was a...
yeah, I mean there's just an איסור issur for you to do,
right, you to benefit. Okay, so now what do we have? We
have this this animal that had full קדושה kedusha. and was then
redeemed. It has residual קדושה kedusha, to the expression that number one,
you can't use it in any way when it's alive. You can
are only allowed to slaughter and eat from it, whether you can
even make it into dog food and you can redeem it for
that purpose is a question. And because of the residual קדושה, kedusha,
it's exempt from בכור bechor and it's exempt from מתנות. matanot. Now
we get to the issue about not working it, but again this
issue about ולדות וחלב. vladot v'chalav. If it actually gave birth or
let's say you did milk it, although we're going to really focus
on giving birth, there's one issue of an איסור issur for you
to do the act. You're not allowed to work it, to shear
it, and so on. There's another question about what's the status of
the things that it produces. And the best example is let's say
in this one where you actually you didn't do anything, it just
gave birth. Can you benefit from the product? Which is not the
same as the previous question, which is are you allowed to do
the act? So the משנה says their children are for the the
children and the milk is forbidden. And again... And presumably even after
you redeemed it, if it gives birth or it gives off milk,
it gives milk, it remains forbidden, and that would again be this
point of the residual קדושה. kedusha, Let's see how the גמרא Gemara
continues with this.
ולדותיהן וחלבן אסור לאחר פדיונן, Veladoteihen v'chalban asur l'achar pidyonan, their children
and their milk is forbidden even after it has been redeemed, it
still has residual קדושה. kedusha So the גמרא Gemara says, היכי דמי?
Heichi dami? What's the case after it's been redeemed?
אילימא דעבר וילד לאחר פדיונן, Ilima d'abar v'yalad l'achar pidyonan, everything happened
after it was redeemed, right, it became pregnant and then gave birth
and then also began to lactate. אמאי? Amai? Why is it forbidden?
Although it's true that it has some residual קדושה, kedusha but ולד
צבי ואיל נינהו. Velad tzvi v'ayal ninhu. Let's go back to the
תורה Torah comparing it to a deer. If a deer has children
or gives milk, it's permissible. So if everything happened once it was
redeemed, so although there is some residual קדושה, kedusha that should not
forbid the children. Okay, that we know, it doesn't allow you to
milk it, it doesn't allow you to work it, to shear it,
but it's compared to this צבי ואיל, tzvi v'ayal, it should be
permissible.
אלא דעבר לפני פדיון, Ela d'abar lifnei pidyon, it became pregnant before
it was redeemed, so it was when the fetus had some of
the original
קדושה, kedusha וילדה לאחר פדיון, v'yalda l'achar pidyon, then it was redeemed
and then it was born. Okay, so if the whole thing happened
after it was redeemed, it's enough out of the category that the
children are totally untouched. But if it started before it was redeemed,
that קדושה kedusha remains in the children as well, and even the
children remain forbidden.
Both the children and also the חלב, chalav, okay.
Well, but we're going to talk about, let's talk about what is
exactly the status of the children. So now the גמרא Gemara, first
says, הא לפני פדיון מקדש נמי קדשי. Ha lifnei pidyon mikdash nami
kadshi. But that would suggest, which is not a big חידוש, chiddush,
that if it got pregnant and gave birth before, everything before it
was redeemed, then the child would have the קדושה kedusha, of the
mother. Okay, that's opposed to saying the child is forbidden, which is
what we say when it was half before and half after. If
it was fully done before it was redeemed, then maybe the child,
the same way the mother's a קרבן, korban maybe the child has
the קדושה kedusha. of a קרבן korban. as well. And this gets
us to a question which we raised yesterday, which is a child
born to an animal that's a קרבן, korban. does the child also
have the קדושה kedusha of a קרבן? korban. You remember last time
we learned it from a פסוק of אם תצא ועד אל המקום
אשר Im tetzei v'ad el hamakom asher whatever the פסוק was, which
was basically saying that even the ולד velad of a קדשים kodashim
has קדושה kedusha of a קרבן korban, and it can be brought
as a קרבן. korban, So now we're making the same point here
when it all happened prior. מנא הני מילי? Mina hanei mili? Where
do we know this from? דתנו רבנן, D'tanu rabbanan, זכר, Zachar, it
says by a שלמים, shlamim, it says you should bring it male
or female. So we understand that that verse is extra. As long
as you don't limit me, I'll understand it's male or female. Why
does the תורה have to say male or female? So זכר לרבות
את הולד. Zachar l'rabot et havelad. Tell me that even the child,
it's a pretty funny thing to include from the word זכר. zachar.
Anyway,
well, there you go. Okay, anyway, so זכר zachar includes even a
child. נקבה, Nekevah, and it says female לרבות את התמורה, l'rabot et
hatmurah, even an exchange. Okay, so something that has a derivative קדושה,
kedusha and there's two ways to have a derivative קדושה. kedusha You
try to do an exchange, it didn't remove it from the original
but it applied to the second, or the child. Those types of
derivative קדושה kedusha are still a high enough קדושה kedusha that the
thing can actually, and we're going to discuss it, but at least
yesterday we said can actually be brought as a קרבן. korban. Okay,
so if it all happened before it was redeemed, then this תמורה
or child, both those have a full קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban.
So say you want to do a תמורה on the ולד.
velad. Okay, Michael, we're going to have a whole מסכת תמורה, Masechet
Tmurah, let's bracket that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ואין לי אלא ולד תמימים ותמורת תמימים. V'ein li ela velad
tmimim u'tmurat tmimim. That's only if it's the child or תמורה of
an unblemished animal, where actually the source of it could be brought
as well. ולד בעלי מומין ותמורת בעלי מומין מניין? Velad baalei mumin
u'tmurat baalei mumin minayin? How do you know if the mother has
a מום mum that the קדושה kedusha applies to the child? And
again, as long as the מום mum. came afterwards, it's not a
מום mum. that impinges on the קדושה kedusha. of the mother. Remember,
if it had the מום mum first and then was sanctified, we
learned yesterday that the child does not have a קדושה kedusha to
be brought on the altar and you may even can redeem it
even unblemished because its קדושה kedusha was never קדושת מזבח. But here
the mother's קדושה kedusha is קדושת מזבח, it got the מום mum
later but that doesn't impinge on the קדושה. kedusha And therefore, how
do we know that the child has that קדושה kedusha. as
well? כשהוא אומר אם זכר, K'shehu omer im zachar, if, the next
word אם, כתיב זכר ונקבה. Ktiv zachar u'nekevah. Why does it say
אם and אם נקבה? im nekevah? לרבות ולד בעלי מומין, L'rabot velad
baalei mumin, even if the mother has a מום, mum, again a
מום that came after it was sanctified. ואם נקבה לרבות תמורת בעלי
מומין. V'im nekevah l'rabot tmurat baalei mumin. Okay, so now we've got,
now we've got that idea that we said yesterday, which was that
when it's born from a mother ולד קדשים, velad kodashim, when the
mother had the קדושה kedusha full קדושה kedusha to begin with, even
if now it has a blemish, the child has full קדושה kedusha.
and the child can even be brought as a קרבן. korban. We
made that point yesterday as well from a different פסוק, and the
same by תמורה, those are compared because those are both derivative קדושה.
kedusha, And here again, it's critical whether the מום of the mother
happened before or after. If it happened after,
the קדושה kedusha is unimpinged, and therefore full. Now we're going to
go to our more middle case, which is more complex, which is
that it was pregnant when it was unredeemed, it gave birth after
redeeming, and this and that child is forbidden because it had the
full קדושה kedusha. to begin with, then it was redeemed, then it
remains forbidden now that it's born. Now we're going to try to
figure out what exactly is the story with this child that was
in this middle category. ולדות שלאחר פדיון מאי תיהא עליה. vladot she'le'achar
pidyon mai te'hei alei. Those children after that were born after it
was redeemed, what's their story? Now let's for a minute
double back and talk about the ones that were born before it
was redeemed and we said had full
קדושה. kedusha לפני פדיונם, lifnei pidyonam, those that were born before it
was redeemed and had full קדושה, kedusha actually there's a question about
their status. מפלגי פליגי בה, miflag palgi bah, there there's a debate.
איכא למאן דאמר, ika l'man d'amar, there are those that say קדשי
להקרבה, kadshi l'hakravah, you can even bring it as a קרבן, korban
which is what we said in the ברייתא braisa yesterday, that it's
ממש full קדושה kedusha and you can bring it as a קרבן,
korban. this derivative קדושה. kedusha. ואיכא למאן דאמר קדשי לרעייה, ve'ika l'man
d'amar kadshi l'reia, that some say that no, that you have to
go ahead and you still can't bring it, it's derivative קדושה kedusha
and therefore you have to let it walk around and graze till
it gets a מום and then redeem it. Now that's not the
thrust of everything we've been saying, but there is those that say
that this derivative קדושה kedusha cannot directly be brought as a קרבן.
korban. Fine, that's in the event when it was born beforehand and
certainly the simple sense is that if it was born before it
was redeemed it's full קדושה kedusha. and it can even be brought
as a קרבן. korban, But now let's talk about the more complex
case when it was born after it was redeemed. However, לאחר פדיונם
מאי תיהא עליהם, l'achar pidyonam mai te'hei aleihem, what's the story when
it was born after it was redeemed? So אמר רב כהנא, Amar
Rav Kahuna, now what's the issue? The issue is like במה נפשך,
b'mai nafshach, right? Clearly you can't bring it as a קרבן korban,
because the mother was redeemed and it only has residual קדושה. kedusha
So there's no question you're not bringing it as a קרבן. korban?
Now how about the idea about what?
Can't you just sanctify it?
Ah, so that's another issue, which is you cannot just sanctify something
that already has what's called קדושה דחויה. kedusha dchuya. Once it has
sanctity that was derailed, you cannot now say oh let's just give
it a new level of sanctity. That already is sort of like
there's this whole concept of דחוי, dichuy, once something was pushed away
it can never be fit again. You cannot just say I'll salvage
it, I'll sanctify it now and bring it as a קרבן. korban.
It can't be brought as a קרבן, korban that's number one. How
about saying well maybe I would say the most obvious thing to
be saying, it would be like the mother, no, it would be
that it would be what do you call it, it would be
you can't do גיזה ועבודה giza va'avoda but you can שחט shecht
it and benefit from it. But that raises the maybe you can,
but that raises the question of did the act of redeeming the
mother also mean that the fetus was redeemed as well? And if
you say not, that only the mother was redeemed and not the
fetus, then think about the bizarre nature of this case. The fetus
had full קדושה kedusha because
it was growing when the animal was not redeemed and then it
was with its full קדושה kedusha it was born to a mother
that did not have full קדושה. kedusha So that really puts it
in this bizarre case about what can you do with it.
Okay, to depend on the מחלוקת machlokes of עובר ירך אמו.
ubar yerech imo. Well that could be and it could be that
if it was redeemed with the mother its status will be more
obvious, it'll be just like the mother's. So let's take a look.
So אמר רב כהנא כונסן לכיפה ומתים. Amar Rav Kahuna: konsan l'kipa
u'mesim. Okay, you have to lock them in a room and wait
for them to die. Okay, which is now every time this comes
up, there's the very understandable objection about whatever happened to צער בעלי
חיים? tzaar baalei chayim? And the answer is well first of all
there's a debate in the גמרא Gemara whether צער בעלי חיים tzaar
baalei chayim is דאורייתא d'oraisa or not and second of all even
if צער בעלי חיים tzaar baalei chayim is דאורייתא, d'oraisa, the גמרא,
Gemara at least ראשונים rishonim are okay with the idea, the גמרא
Gemara is never explicit, that it's legitimate when it's serving certain higher
goals and certain benefits. And here the benefit of not transgressing is
considered to be an important benefit. Of course it is really,
however much you consider rationally explain it, it is a little disturbing
to talk about this, but nevertheless that's what רב כהנא Rav Kahuna
says, you have to let it die, there's nothing that can be
done for it. You certainly can't bring it as a קרבן, korban
you can't even redeem it. Why not? Let's take a look.
Okay, he says דהיכי ליעביד, de'heichi le'avid, what do you want to
do with these things? לקרבינהו, le'karvinhu, first of all you want to
bring it as a קרבן? korban. מכח קדושה דחויה קאתו. mikoch kedusha
dchuya ka'atu.
That can't be because again he's assuming by the way if it
was redeemed with the mother it would make it a lot easier,
then presumably it would have the exact same status as the mother.
But we're assuming no, no, only the mother was redeemed, it had
full קדושה kedusha initially, but then was born to, part of the
reason it has full קדושה kedusha. is derivative קדושה kedusha from the
mother. Okay, so it actually started with full קדושה kedusha but now
its derivative קדושה kedusha was derailed because the mother was redeemed. So
מכח קדושה דחויה קאתו, mikoch kedusha dchuya ka'atu, they're coming from sanctity
that was derailed. So therefore it cannot be brought as a קרבן.
korban.
לפרקינהו, le'farkinhu, why don't you just redeem it and make our life
easy? Or at least even if you want to wait for a
מום, okay, that's called רעייה, reia, let it graze till it gets
a מום and then redeem it, that should solve the problem. No,
לא אלימי למתפס פדיונם. lo alimi l'mispas pidyonam. Here's an interesting concept,
it's not strong enough to seize redemption. used to transfer onto the
קדושה. kedusha If somehow the קדושה kedusha is so residual, right when
it's real קדושה kedusha that it's standing to be used as a
certain purpose, then I can transfer to money and use the money
to that purpose. But if basically it's so residual and so derailed,
I can't do an act of redeeming because it's not like the
קדושה kedusha is going anywhere. Okay, so meaning what?
Because the mother was used to be more קדוש kadosh and now
is not then?
And because when it was born, it was born with this קדושה
kedusha. that came from a redeemed amp... it's like not just a
קדושה kedusha like the mother had a מום. It's a קדושה kedusha
that the mother actually had the קדושה kedusha removed from it. I
mean there was residual קדושה. kedusha, Okay, so therefore, now of course
what the interesting thing is, we would have said fine, treat it
like the mother, שחט shecht it and eat it and end of
story. And treat it like the mother. But he's assuming not, he's
assuming that it is independent of the mother. If it's independent of
the mother, so it has like קדושת מזבח, but that was totally
derailed. It's even worse than a מום. Because it ended off with
the קדושה kedusha that had been removed from the mother. And therefore
because it had been so derailed, you can't certainly you can't bring
it as a קרבן korban, and you can't even redeem it. So
what are you going to do with it?
Can't you just let it leave its life out there in peace?
Well, right, so why not just why not just let it graze
and don't do anything? Then what the only reason you lock it
in a room is because you're afraid that somebody's going to misuse
it, right? If it's forbidden in benefit, you're afraid for misuse. So
to protect us from misuse, you lock it in a room and
you let it die.
But in the case before we let it graze,
but that's because that's because first of all you let it graze
in an area where there's a lot of barbed wire and whatever.
So it gets the מום pretty quickly. So it gets the מום
pretty quickly and there the problem will be solved quickly enough as
opposed to having to keep it around for its entire life and
never and you know you'll never solve it, that we say let's
just solve the problem now, lock it in a room. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara so what are you going to do with
it? So אמי ומר ודבי ארץ ישראל בשמיה דרבי חנינא, Ami ve-Mar
u-de-bei Eretz Yisrael bishmei de-Rabbi Chanina, סמוך לפדיונם מתפיסן לשם אותו זבח.
samuch le-pidyonam matpisan leshem oso zevach. Right before you redeem it, you
sanctify it for the קרבן korban that it was going that its
mother was going to be, which is basically what Michael was suggesting,
which is just add a level of קדושה kedusha? and then bring
it for and bring it as the קרבן. korban. If its mother
was going to be a שלמים, shelamim, which is probably the only
thing it could be because that's a female, so make this a
שלמים shelamim and then even after it's redeemed it'll still have קדושת
שלמים kedushas shelamim and blah. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
what do you mean redeemed? We just said you can't redeem it.
So the גמרא Gemara says אותו זבח לשם זבח
סמוך לפדיונם oso zevach leshem zevach samuch le-pidyonam right before you've redeemed
it, למימר דבני פדיה נינהו? le-meimar de-benei pidya ninu? You think you
can redeem it? We just got through saying you can't redeem it.
So no, here's an alternative. אלא אימא סמוך לפדיון אמן מתפיסן לשם
אותו זבח. Ella eima samuch le-pidyon imam matpisan leshem oso zevach. Ah,
now you understand this is actually a brilliant suggestion. What is the
reason it got derailed? Because the mother was redeemed and part of
its קדושה kedusha derives from the mother. Before you do anything to
the mother and derail this fetus, sanctify the fetus now in the
mother's womb and say I am giving it its independent, not derivative
קדושה, kedusha, which is what it had up until now, I'm giving
it independent קדושה kedusha of שלמים. shelamim. And then you redeem the
mother. So now what happens? Now who needs the derivative קדושה? kedusha
Right? So who cares that it has its independent קדושה kedusha. and
the mother's status is irrelevant and then it's born and it's a
שלמים. shelamim. Now you can't do that after it's born because after
it's born and it already has
derivative derailed קדושה, kedusha once it's דחויה dechuya you can't bring it
back. Right? Once it's pushed away it can't come back. Then you
put it in the כיפה. kipa. But if it but before it
gets derailed, before there's any problem, give it an independent קדושה kedusha,
and then what happens to the mother is irrelevant. What a great
solution. Okay, so let's take a look. So so the גמרא Gemara
says טעמא מאי? ta'ama mai? So I'm sorry did I skip a
line? אלא אימא... Ella eima... yeah no... טעמא מאי. ta'ama mai. Now
what's the reason for this? Now it's a little bit of a
question about what's the reason for what? Let's read the answer. רש"י
Rashi has three explanations of what the question is about. Let's read
the answer and then work backwards. So אמר רב לוי, amar Rav
Levi, so רב לוי Rav Levi said גזירה שמא יגדל מהן עדרים
עדרים. gezeira shema yigadel me-hen adarim adarim. We're afraid that you're going
to graze flocks of them. So what's the reason for what? So
רש"י Rashi said well one question is maybe what's the reason like
like Michael said why do we lock it in a כיפה? kipa?
Why don't we just let it graze around and die? And the
answer is no no you let it graze around and die, it's
going to have kids and the kids are going to have kids
and eventually somebody's going to transgress with this thing. You gotta just
solve the problem quickly and get it out of the way even
though it means locking the animal in a כיפה. kipa. Okay that's
one answer that רש"י Rashi says.
So another one explanation. Another explanation is that's probably the easiest one
and that's also saying like why or okay and then the other
explanation is one minute let me just quickly
רש"י Rashi you won't kill it because it has קדושה kedusha and
you shouldn't be doing that?
Yeah you can't destroy something that has קדושה. kedusha You can let
it die but you can't actively destroy it.
Right. Like that what I just gave you is the second answer
of רש"י Rashi which is certainly the easiest explanation. Why do we
bother with anything? Just let it live and live out its life.
And then the third I'll skip the first but the third one
which רש"י Rashi likes the best
is one minute let me just notice
so the third one is and it's important to notice so... It's
actually saying, questioning our whole assumption. Our whole assumption that this child
has this in-between status and it's דחוי duchuy and you can't do
anything, רש"י Rashi says, why do you say that? Why not say
when you redeemed the mother, it affected, it was, you redeemed the
child as well? And since you redeemed the child as well, the
status of the child is the same as the status of the
mother. Why do you create this crazy idea that has in, you
know, derivative קדושה kedusha, but it's not exactly like the mother and
you can't do anything with it? Why shouldn't we say the simplest
thing, which any of us would have said, which is what's the
status of the child? The same as the mother. If the mother
was redeemed, it affected the fetus as well. And to that the
answer is, no, we don't want that to be true because then
if you have, if you have a mother and you שחטed shecht
it and you, you know, you're going to use it right away,
you'll be done with it. But what happens if it gives birth
to a child? You don't want to שחט shecht the child right
away, it's a loss of good meat, right? So you're going to,
so if we tell you you're allowed to שחט shecht it and
benefit from it like the mother, you'll wait till it grows up
and it's a, you know, and you get more benefit and it
grazes. What's going to happen in the process of it growing up?
It's going to mate with another animal, it's going to have kids,
and it's going to get out of hand because you're not going
to be able to keep track of which of these things has
this status or not. So therefore we basically wanted you to not
say treat it like the mother, we wanted you to deal with
it right away. So the dealing with it right away is either
locking it in the כיפה kippah or it is the giving of
the sanctity and bringing of a קרבן. korban, Now again, רש"י likes
that third explanation. I think it's a little bit strange because the
גמרא Gemara is taking it as an assumption that this thing is
not like the mother and then to say that we're sort of
questioning that assumption is funny. I think the easier explanation is just
why do we have to deal with it right away? Why not
just wait? And there the answer is we don't want to wait.
If you wait, you'll get in trouble. Okay, so now we have,
so but now that's what we say now you do with this
fetus. So basically what's the story? This animal was born to the
mother. What is the story? So the גמרא assumes that that means
that it is not like the mother. You cannot שחט shecht it
and eat it. It has somewhat of independent, its derivative קדושה, kedusha.
but it wasn't redeemed with the mother. And the fact that it
wasn't redeemed and it has derivative קדושה kedusha puts it in a
very in-between category and the only way to solve it is lock
it up and let it die or to sanctify it before it
gets into trouble. Okay, and therefore, you know, if you're smart enough
and you sanctify it before it gets into trouble, you can give
it its own status. Why not just let it graze its whole
life? Because that's going to lead you into trouble. Okay, now we
move on.
And again, if it was before, if it gave birth before it
was redeemed, so that was also a מחלוקת, machlokes, right?
Yeah, it was a מחלוקת. machlokes. The simple sense is you could
bring it as a קרבן, korban but that's a מחלוקת. machlokes. Okay,
now the גמרא says like this. בעי מיניה רבינא מרב ששת. Ba'ei
minei Ravina me-Rav Sheshet. רבינא Ravina asked from רב ששת. Rav Sheshet.
מה שמתפיסן לחזור ושיחצה. Mah she-matpisan le-chozer ve-she-yirtzeh. Now, let's say you
want to not make the fetus not this קרבן korban of the
mother. You're going to solve it the way you suggested. You're about
to redeem the mother. You want to not have a child that
is in this in-between status and this not solvable status, so you
sanctify it before it gives birth. Let's say I want to sanctify
it as an עולה, olah, not as a שלמים. shelamim. Am I
allowed to do that or not? If I'm giving it independent status,
why not? Okay, so אמר ליה אין מתפיסין. amar lei ein matpisin.
No, sorry, can't do it. מאי טעמא? Why not? אמר ליה גמר
בשעריך בשעריך. amar lei gemar bisharecha bisharecha. It's a verse from, it
says your
gates. מבכור. mibechor. מה בכור אין מתפיסין לחזור ושיחצה. mah bechor ein
matpisin le-chozer ve-she-yirtzeh. The Torah says that you cannot sanctify a בכור
bechor for another קרבן. korban, It says it explicitly. דכתיב אך בכור
אשר יבכר לה' בבהמה לא יקדיש איש אתו. de-chtiv ach bechor asher
yerubak la-Hashem bivehemah lo yakdish ish oto. You shall not sanctify a
בכור bechor and add another קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. That even if
you're not going to remove קדושת בכור, kedushat bechor, let's say you
make your בכור, bechor, I'll double up, I'll make it a בכור
bechor and a שלמים shelamim and I'll bring it, I'm going to
do the same thing, I'll eat it, who cares? Right? No, no,
no, you cannot add a קדושה kedusha, to בכור. bechor. That's what
the Torah tells you. So the same way that's true, and the
verse says you shall eat the בכור bechor in your gates if
it has a blemish, and it says you eat פסולי מוקדשים psulei
mukdashim in your gates, the same verse speaks about in your gates
meaning in your cities, not have to be in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
the same way by a בכור bechor you cannot add a level
of קדושה, kedusha that גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah tells us אף הני
נמי אין מתפיסין לחזור ושיחצה. af hani nami ein matpisin le-chozer ve-she-yirtzeh.
You cannot add a different level of קדושה. kedusha Since it does
have derivative קדושה kedusha from the mother, even though you're sanctifying it
in utero and you're giving it independent קדושה, kedusha. it cannot be
different from the קדושה kedusha. that it also has, the derivative קדושה
kedusha, it also has from the mother. In the same way a
בכור, bechor, you understand also it's a nice analogy, gets קדושה kedushah,
not from the mother, the mother wasn't קרבן, korban. but by virtue
of the mother, and do not give it an additional קדושה. kedushah
There too, do not give it an additional קדושה. kedushah You can
give it independent, but it has to be the same. Okay, so
now the גמרא says like this. תניא
נמי כוותיה דרב ששת. Tanya nami ke-vatah de-Rav Sheshet. We turn like
רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. קדשים שקדם מום קבוע להקדשן. Kodshim she-kadam mum
kavua le-hakdeshan. And this is going to be a ברייתא braita that
basically reviews our entire two משניות. mishnayot. Let's try to read this
pretty quickly, although I know it's 8:30 already, but anyway let's just
do this. If קדשים, kodshim, if first the blemish began before the
קדושה, kedushah that's the first half of our משנה, ונפדו, venifdu, it
was redeemed, חייבין בבכור ובמתנות. chayavin be-bechor u-ve-matanot. You give בכור bechor
and מתנות, matanot, right? It's a full, nothing residual. בין לפני פדיונן
בין לאחר פדיונן. Bein lifnei pidyonan bein le-achar pidyonan.
Whether that's after you've redeemed it. Now, both before and after you've
redeemed it, הגוזז והעובד בהן אינו סופג את הארבעים. hagozez ve-oveid ba-hen
eino soveg et ha-arba'im. If you shear and work
with them, you
don't receive the
forty. Maybe there's a rabbinic issue, but you don't get lashes even
before it's redeemed because it is not a קרבן korban. in where
the act of shearing is per se prohibited. בין לפני פדיונן ובין
לאחר פדיונן, bein lifnei pidyonan u'vein l'achar pidyonan, whether before or after
you've redeemed it, אינו עושה תמורה, you don't make a תמורה, תמורה
is only by קדשי מזבח. ולפני פדיונן, v'lifnei pidyonan, before it's been
redeemed, מועלין בהן, moalin bahen, you do get, you do transgress מעילה,
me'ilah, it is sanctified for the, for the temple. ולאחר פדיונן, u'l'achar
pidyonan, after it's been redeemed, אין מועלין בהן ein moalin bahen because
there's no residual קדושה, kedushah so after it's redeemed there is no
misuse of הקדש hekdesh funds. ולדותיהם חול, v'ladoseihem chol, if they give
birth after it's been redeemed, their children are completely de-sac, de-sanctified, are
completely neutral. ונפדים תמימים, v'nifdim tmimim, the children can be redeemed even
with a blemish. Remember we mentioned that yesterday. The children that are
born after this thing has been redeemed, I'm sorry, the children that
are born before it's redeemed can be, can be, can be redeemed
without a blemish. Since the קדושה kedushah. that the children have is
not קדושה kedushah that can be ever brought to the altar because
it's coming from the mother that's קדושה kedushah was never קדושת מזבח,
the children as well can be redeemed even if they are unblemished.
ומפיסין לכל זבח שירצה. u'matpisin l'chol zevach she'yirtzeh. Once they've been redeemed,
then, and then, and then you can go ahead and make this
animal that had קדושת דמים, not קדושת מזבח, now you can give
it, you can make it into any קרבן korban. you want if
you wanted to. Once you've redeemed it and removed it from קדושת
דמים.
Doesn't go on the children?
No.
כללו של דבר הרי הן כחולין לכל דבריהם. klalo shel davar harei
hen k'chulin l'chol divreihem. Bottom line is once these have been redeemed,
completely nothing residual, total חולין. chulin. אין לך בהם אלא מצות פדיון
בלבד. ein l'cha bahem ela mitzvas pidyon bilvad. The only thing you're
supposed to do with these things is redeem them and then the
money gets used for a קרבן, but after, but after, but after
that nothing is residual.
פדיון להעלות? pidyon l'ha'alot?
I don't know, there's a question exactly what it means. Raise up
the money, I don't know. אבל קדש הקדישן בעל מום, aval kodesh
hikdishan ba'al mum, however if first you were sanctified and then it
got the blemish, which is the second part of our משנה, what
we're dealing with, או מום עובר להקדישן ולאחר מכאן נולד מום קבוע,
o mum over l'hikdishan v'achar mikan nolad mum kavua, or transitory then
they were sanctified then a fixed מום, ונפדו v'nifdu and now it
was redeemed. Now you have residual קדושה kedushah, because it started with
full קדושה. kedushah פטורה מן הבכור ומן המתנות, ptura min habechor u'min
hamatanot, you're exempt from בכור bechor and מתנות. matanot. בין, bein, now,
בין לפני פדיונן ובין לאחר פדיונן, bein lifnei pidyonan u'vein l'achar pidyonan,
whether before or after they've redeemed, הגוזז ועובד בהן סופג את הארבעים,
hagozez v'oveid bahen sofeg et ha'arba'im, you get lashes for shearing it
or working it even if you didn't derive benefit, right? The act
of shearing, the act of working you get lashes because that is
the story with a קרבן. Forget the prohibition of מעילה, me'ilah, it
is, the act of shearing and of working is prohibited even after
it's been redeemed, that's what we said, it has the residual קדושה
kedushah, and you get lashes. ובין לפני פדיונן ובין לאחר פדיונן, u'vein
lifnei pidyonan u'vein l'achar pidyonan, whether before or after, עושים תמורה, osim
tmurah, it makes a תמורה even after it's been redeemed. The residual
קדושה kedushah is enough that if you try to make a תמורה
that would apply to the other animal. לפני פדיונן מועלין בהן ולאחר
פדיונן אין מועלין בהן. lifnei pidyonan moalin bahen u'l'achar pidyonan ein moalin
bahen. Before it's been redeemed there's מעילה, me'ilah, after it's been redeemed
although there's residual קדושה, kedushah there still is no מעילה me'ilah because
it's only residual. I mean it means that you can't use it
in certain ways and you get lashes but there's no מעילה, me'ilah,
it's not really fully קדוש anymore. ולדותיהם קדש, v'ladoseihem kodesh, their children
are sanctified even if they were born after redemption. ואין נפדים תמימים,
v'ein nifdim tmimim, you cannot redeem the children if they are
unblemished, okay? ואין מפיסין לכל זבח שירצה. v'ein matpisin l'chol zevach she'yirtzeh.
And here, the whole reason we quoted this ברייתא although it was
a nice review was for the last line. You cannot sanctify the
children for a different type of a קרבן. Okay, it might even
mean by the way, it might even also refer to the mother
after it's been redeemed. But either way once something has this קדושה
kedushah. of one type, you cannot add to it now a different
קדושה, whether it's the residual קדושה of the mother, the derivative קדושה
of the child, even if you sanctify it, you know, before it's
born, you cannot do it as a different קרבן. כללו של דבר
הרי הן כהקדש לכל דבריהם. klalo shel davar harei hen k'hekdesh l'chol
divreihem. They are like הקדש hekdesh fully even though they have a
blemish and even after they're redeemed they have residual קדושה. ואין לך
בהם אלא היתר אכילה בלבד. v'ein l'cha bahem ela heter achilah bilvad.
Even after you've redeemed it, all you're allowed to do with it
is eat it. With that we will end. Okay.
Doesn't go on the kids because the first case was a מום
קבוע, mum kavua, can't מפיס. matpis.